[MUSIC]
The box model is the basis of CSS layout
because it
dictates how elements are displayed and
how they interact with each other.
Think of each element on the page as a
rectangular box.
Each box has certain dimensions and takes
up a certain amount of space.
Now, the space the box takes up depends on
its content, and
the padding borders and margins that may
surround the content.
So the box model is what describes the
amount of space each
element takes up on the page.
So, let's dig a little deeper into this
concept by going over the main
components that make up the CSS box model.
The very basis of designing with CSS is
understanding the box model concept.
So, as I mentioned earlier,
we'll need to begin thinking of every HTML
element on the page as a box.
And as you can see here, if we apply a red
border to every element on our page,
each element is made up of a rectangle or
a box.
So, in order to effectively understand the
CSS box model concept,
we need to know the two ways elements are
naturally displayed.
So, every element has a display value,
depending on what type of element it is.
The default for most elements is usually
block or inline.
Now, block elements form a separate block
that takes up
the full width available based on the
width of its parent element, and
it creates a new line before and after the
element.
Some examples of block elements are divs,
paragraph, any heading tag, or list items.
So, notice how the block-level divs on our
page, as well as the headings and
lists are taking up an entire line of
content.
They're also forcing a new line of content
before and after the element.
And we can see that as well down here in
our footer div.
Now, inline elements only take up as much
width as they need to.
They don't force any new lines, and they
stay inline with the rest of the content.
Some examples of inline elements are span
tags, images, and anchor elements.
So, notice how the anchor element, or
linked boxes, stay in line with the rest
of the content in our paragraph.
The same thing happens up top in our title
span element.
Notice how its width only takes up the
space of its content.
And the reason it's displayed on its own
line is because there's a block-level h1
element underneath it.
The block-level h1 is forcing the new
line.
So now let's discuss how padding, borders,
and
margins interact with each to form a box
because it's important to understand.
[SOUND] The box in the box model is made
of
four distinct parts that calculate its
size.
And visually, it's rather simple as we can
see here.
The innermost area and core component of
the box is the content area, [SOUND] which
is the area containing the element's
actual content, like text or an image.
Surrounding that content area is the
[SOUND] padding area.
Padding is often used to give the content
area some breathing room by
separating the content from the
surrounding border area.
And the border area of [SOUND] the box is
the outermost part of the box.
You can think of it as an outline to the
box.
Although borders are optional, different
styles like color and
thickness can be applied to them.
Finally, the [SOUND] margin area exists
outside of the box.
It's this space around an element that
separates it from other elements.
So the most important thing to remember
here is
[SOUND] the padding area creates space
inside the box,
while the margin area [SOUND] creates
space outside and around the box.
So, as we can see, padding, borders, and
margins are important components of the
CSS box model.
They are the properties that essentially
wrap the content area of a box.
So, now that we've covered the main
properties of the box model,
we're ready to put these concepts to work.
That's coming up next.